A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Medicine, 1993-2019.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Minutes of the Virginia Board of Medicine,
1993-2019.
The Library of Virginia
45474, 51024, 53923, 54012
Virginia. Dept. of Health Professions.
8.2 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 45474 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 04/07/2011.
Accession 51024 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 09/13/2013.
Accession 53923 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 06/21/2023.
Accession 54012 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 10/23/2023.
Historical Information
Regulation of the health professions began late in the nineteenth century. On January 31, 1884, the General Assembly passed an act creating the Board of Medical Examiners to certify physicians for practice in Virginia. In 1973 the name was changed to the Board of Medicine.
The Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 31, 1977, to provide administrative services to the health regulatory boards of the state. The boards continue to regulate their professions through the examination, licensing, and disciplining of the practitioners of health science. In 1986, the Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards became the Dept. of Health Professions. Its mission is to enhance the delivery of safe and competent health care by licensing qualified health care professionals, enforcing standards of practice, and providing information to both practitioners and consumers of health care services.
Scope and Content
Minutes, 1993-2017, include official minutes and related attachments documenting the meetings, activities, discussions and policy decisions and recommendations of the Virginia Board of Medicine. Includes minutes for standing committees and other groups (Executive Committee, Finance Committee, Legislative/Regulatory Committee, Committee of the Joint Boards of Nursing and Medicine, Credentials Committee, Committee on Certification of Clinical Psychologists), and other groups (Ad Hoc Committee on HIV; Ad Hoc Committee on Buprenorphine (2016-2017), Ad Hoc Committee on Ethics (2003), Advisory Committee on Certification of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons), as well as records related to informal conferences, telephone conferences, and formal hearings. Attachments may include agendas, articles, bylaws, correspondence, draft minutes, financial statements, legislation, memoranda of understanding, polices, public hearing comments, presentations, publications, regulations/regulatory reviews, reports, revenue reports and workshop materials.
May also contain minutes and related attachments for Advisory Boards for Accupuncture, Athletic Training, Behavioral Analysts, Chiropractors, Genetic Counseling, Health Correctional Assistants, Midwifery, Occupational Therapy, Optometry, Physical Therapy, Physician Assistants, Polysomnography Technology, Radiological Technology, Rehabilitation Providers, Respiratory Therapy and Sexual Offender Treatment Providers.
Contents List
- Minutes of the Virginia Board of Medicine, 1993-2017.
  - Accession 45474 (1993-2005)., Extent: 5.25 cu. ft. (15 boxes)
    Includes original, signed minutes, 1993-2005, for the full board as well as for committees and advisory boards. Also includes board meeting packet attachments.
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1993 Feb 4-6. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1993 Feb 4-6. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 1993 June 3-6 (Part I). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 1993 June 3-6 (Part II). (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 1993 Oct 7-10. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1994 Feb 10-12. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1994 Feb 10-12. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part III), 1994 Feb 10-12. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part IV), 1994 Feb 10-12. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1994 June 9-11. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1994 June 9-11. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1994 Oct 13-15. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1994 Oct 13-15. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 1995 Feb 9-11. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 1995 June 8-10. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 1995 Oct 12-14. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 1996 Feb 8-10. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 1996 June 6-8. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 1996 Oct 3-5. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1997 Feb 6-8. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1997 Feb 6-8. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1997 June 5-7. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1997 June 5-7. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 1997 Oct 16-18. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 1998 Feb 5-7. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1998 June 4-6. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part ), 1998 June 4-6. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1998 Oct 8-10. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1998 Oct 8-10. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 1999 Feb 11-13. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1999 June 3-5. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1999 June 3-5. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 1999 Oct 14-16. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 1999 Oct 14-16. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 2000 Feb 10-12. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2000 June 8-10. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2000 June 8-10. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes, 2000 Oct 12-14. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes, 2001 Feb 8-10. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 2001 June 7-9. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 2001 Oct 11-13. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 2002 Feb 7-9. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 2002 June 6-8. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes, 2002 Oct 10-12. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 2003 Feb 6-8. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 2003 June 5-7. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Board Workshop, 2003 Sept 12-13. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 2003 Oct 9-11. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Executive Committee minutes, 2003 Dec 5. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Ethics minutes, 2003 Dec 12. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 2004 Jan 22-24. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2004 Feb-Mar. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2004 Apr 22-24. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2004 Apr 22-24. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2004 May. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2004 Jun 24-26. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2004 June 24-26. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2004 Sept. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2004 Oct 14-16. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2004 Oct 14-16. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Full Board minutes, 2005 Feb 11-13. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2005 Feb. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2005 Apr. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2005 July 14-16. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2005 July 14-16. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Full Board minutes (Part III), 2005 July 14-16. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2005 Aug. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Minutes - Advisory Boards, 2005 Oct-Dec. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Full Board minutes (Part I), 2005 Nov 17-19. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes (Part II), 2005 Nov 17-19. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Accession 51024 (2008)., Extent: .35 cu. ft. (1 box)
    Includes Minutes, 2008, for the full board as well as for committees and advisory boards.
    - Full Board minutes, 2008 Feb 21-23. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2008 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Full Board minutes, 2008 June 26-28. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2008 June. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 2008 Oct 23-25. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2008 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Accession 53923 (2016-2017).
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2016 Feb 1-5. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Board minutes, 2016 Feb 18-20. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Buprenorphine (1 of 3), 2016 May 13. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Buprenorphine (2 of 3), 2016 May 13. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Buprenorphine (3 of 3), 2016 May 13. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Board minutes (1 of 2), 2016 June 16-18. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board minutes (2 of 2), 2016 June 16-18. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Advisory Board minutes (1 of 2), 2016 June 6-10. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Advisory Board minutes (2 of 2), 2016 June 6-10. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Advisory Board minutes (1 of 2), 2016 Oct 3-7. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Advisory Board minutes (2 of 2), 2016 Oct 3-7. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Board minutes (1 of 3), 2016 Oct 20-22. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Board minutes (2 of 3), 2016 Oct 20-22. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Board minutes (3 of 3), 2016 Oct 20-22. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2017 Jan 30-Feb 3. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Board minutes (1 of 3), 2017 Feb 16-18. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Board minutes (2 of 3), 2017 Feb 16-18. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Board minutes (3 of 3), 2017 Feb 16-18. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Advisory Board minutes (1 of 3), 2017 May 30-June9. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Advisory Board minutes (2 of 3), 2017 May 30-June9. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Advisory Board minutes (3 of 3), 2017 May 30-June9. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Board minutes (1 of 2), 2017 June 22-24. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Board minutes (2 of 2), 2017 June 22-24. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2017 Sept 29-Oct 6. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Board minutes (1 of 3), 2017 Oct 26-28. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Board minutes (2 of 3), 2017 Oct 26-28. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board minutes (3 of 3), 2017 Oct 26-28. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Accession 52014 (2018-2019), Extent: 1.25 cu. ft. (4 boxes)
    Minutes, 2018-2019, for the Full Board and Advisory Boards. Full Board minutes also include minutes for the Executive Committee, Credentials Committee, Legislative Committee and the Ad Hoc Committee on Controlled Substances in Continuing Education (2018 Oct). Advisory Board minutes include the following: Acupuncture, Athletic Training, Behavior Analysis, Genetic Counseling, Midwifery, Occupational Therapy, Physician Assistant, Polysomography Technology, Radiologic Technology and Respiratory Therapy. Includes final, approved minutes with signatures, as well as some draft, unapproved minutes. Minutes may also contain attachments, including revenue and expenditure summaries, correspondence, legislation, presentations, regulations, and reports.
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2018 Jan-Feb. (Box 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 2018 Feb. (Box 1)
    - Full Board minutes, 2018 June. (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2018 June. (Box 2)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2018 Sept-Oct. (Box 2)
    - wFull Board minutes, 2018 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2019 Jan. (Box 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 2019 Feb. (Box 3)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2019 May. (Box 3)
    - Full Board minutes, 2019 June. (Box 3)
    - Advisory Board minutes, 2019 Sept-Oct. (Box 4)
    - Full Board minutes, 2019 Oct. (Box 3)